Guide to the Boris Koutzen Papers, approximately 1916-2010
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Boris Koutzen Papers
approximately 1916-2010
approximately 1916-1966
Koutzen, Boris, 1901-1966
22 cubic feet (63 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Music manuscripts, correspondence, and recordings relating to the life and work of Boris Koutzen.
Biographical Note
Boris Koutzen (1901-1966) was born in Uman, Southern Russia, 1 April 1901. He began composing and studying the violin as a young child, and launched his career as a concert violinist at the age of eleven. His musical education began under his father's tutelage, but in 1918 the family moved to Moscow so Boris could study with Leo Zetlin and Reinhold Glière at the Moscow Conservatory. While a student at the conservatory, Koutzen won the position of first violin in the State Opera House Orchestra, and played for the Moscow Symphony Orchestra under Serge Koussevitzky. Koutzen graduated from the Moscow Conservatory in 1921, studied and played in Germany for two years, then moved to the United States in 1923. His career in the U.S. included playing for the Philadelphia Orchestra under Leopold Stokowski (1924-1927), heading the violin department of the Philadelphia Conservatory (1924-1961), and playing for the NBC Orchestra under Arturo Toscanini (1937-1945). In 1944 he joined the faculty of Vassar College, where he taught violin and conducted the Vassar Orchestra until June 1966. He also taught at Bard College from 1949-1951. Koutzen died of a heart attack 10 December 10 1966 at the age of 65.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of music manuscripts, correspondence, recordings, and other materials relating to the life and work of Boris Koutzen.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College. Department of Music
Subjects:
Composers--United States--correspondence; Violinists--United States--correspondence
Document Types:
Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Correspondence; Phonograph records; Sheet music; Scores (documents for music)
VCL Categories:
Music
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, March 2010. Last updated by Emma Gronbeck, September 2025.
Custodial History
Transferred from the Vassar College Music Library, 2010.
Materials in Series V were transferred from the Vassar College Music Library, 2025. [M2025-013]
Acquisition Information
Original gift from Nadia Koutzen with later accessions in 1999, 2002 and 2010.
Materials in Series V were the gift of Angelika Forndran, 2021, and the Koutzen family.
Other Formats
Series II. "Recordings" has been digitized and the recordings are available to listen to online at the Vassar College Digital Library.
Series List
- Series I. Musical Manuscripts, undated
  This series contains materials related to Koutzen's musical compositions, including drafts, proofs, published copies of scores and librettos.
  Arranged alphabetically by composition title with miscellaneous compositions filed at the end of the sequence.
- Series II. Recordings, 1941-1966
- Series III. Correspondence, Biographical Material and Miscellany, 1955-2002
- Series IV. Additional Accessions from Nadia Koutzen, 1916-1965
- Series V. 2025 Accession, circa 1955-2010
Container List
- SERIES I. Musical Manuscripts
  - Cadenza (for Mozart's "Concerto in G major")
    - Proof (Box 1)
  - Clown's reverie and dance
    - Transparencies (Box 1)
    - Worksheets (Box 1)
  - Concert piece for violoncello and string orchestra
    - Parts (Box 1)
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 1)
    - Ink holograph (Box 1)
    - Pencil holograph (Box 1)
  - Concertante for two solo flutes and orchestra
    - Part (clarinet only) (Box 2)
    - Photocopy of piano reduction (Box 2)
    - Transparencies (orchestra score) (Box 2)
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 2)
    - Published copy (Box 2)
    - Piano-percussion reduction (Box 2)
    - Pencil holograph (Box 2)
    - Solo parts (photo-positives) (Box 3)
    - Solo parts (original ink copies) (Box 3)
    - Solo parts (final ink copies) (Box 3)
    - Worksheets (Box 3)
    - Ink holograph (score) (Box 3)
    - 4 letters to Leon Brazin (Box 3)
  - Concertino for piano and strings
    - Transparencies (original score) (Box 4)
    - Two bound copies (Box 4)
    - Extra parts (not corrected) (Box 4)
    - Manuscript of condensed score and worksheets (Box 4)
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 4)
    - Pen and ink score- "Reduction of orchestra for a second piano" (Box 4)
  - Concerto for five solo instruments and string orchestra
    - Parts (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Original pencil score (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Parts (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Ink holograph (score) (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - 2 bound orchestral scores (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (string parts) (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Concerto for viola and orchestra
    - Transparencies (orchestral score) (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Bound orchestral score (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Solo parts (2 envelopes and wrapped parts) (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Photo-positives (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Ink holograph (parts for strings, flute, and clarinet) (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Worksheets (for 1st, 2nd, and 3rd movements) (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Solo part and piano reduction (transparencies) (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - Concerto for violin and orchestra
    - Photograph of Eugene Ormandy and Boris and Nadia Koutzen (Box 7)
    - Orchestral score (Box 7)
    - Transparencies (orchestral score) (Box 7)
    - Parts (Box 8)
    - Photocopy of solo part (Box 8)
    - Correspondence between Denise Koutzen and Robert Parks (Box 8)
    - Piano arrangement of the score- sketches and worksheets (Box 8)
    - Parts (mimeographed) (Box 9)
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 10)
    - Piano reduction (pencil holograph and ink copy) (Box 10)
    - Transparencies (solo part) (Box 10)
    - Transparencies (solo part and piano reduction) (Box 10)
    - Piano reduction/ worksheets and sketches (Box 10)
    - Concerto for chorus and orchestra without lyrics, just a syllable. (Box 56)
    - Pencil score, not completed (Box 56)
    - Divertimento for orchestra (Box 56)
    - Parts (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (orchestral score) (Box 11 (Oversize))
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Program (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - 3 bound orchestral scores (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Parts (transparencies) (Box 12 (Oversize))
    - Bound volume with sketches for orchestral arrangement and notes regarding instrumentation on score of original version (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Dreamland for voice and piano
    - Pencil manuscript and worksheets (Box 13)
    - Copy of printed sheets (Box 13)
    - Copies of printed sheets marked for performance? (Box 13)
    - Photocopy (Box 13)
    - Transparencies (Box 13)
  - Duo concertante
    - Worksheets (Box 13)
    - Ink holograph transparencies (Box 13)
  - Eidolóns: poem for piano
    - Proofs (Box 13)
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 13)
    - Transparencies (Box 13)
    - Published copy (Box 13)
  - Elegiac rhapsody for orchestra
    - Pencil copy (Box 14)
    - Transparencies (orchestra score) (Box 14)
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 14)
    - 4 bound orchestral scores (Box 14)
  - Enigma for piano
    - Pencil copy (Box 14)
  - Fanfare, prayer, and march
    - Parts (Box 15)
    - Wallpaper bound folder with misc. pencil sketches (Box 15)
    - Full score- 2 bound copies (Box 15)
    - Manuscript- 21 pages (condensed score) and worksheets- 29 pages (Box 15)
    - Individual orchestra parts (Box 15)
    - Transparencies (Box 15)
  - The Fatal oath
    - Piano vocal reduction of orchestral score with text revisions (Box 16)
    - Pencil holograph (orchestral score) and photocopies of three letters- 2 by Rodzinski, 1 by Mitropoulos (Box 16)
    - Libretti: unbound, working copy? (Box 17)
    - Libretti: bound with revisions (Box 17)
    - Libretti: transparencies (Box 17)
    - Libretti: printed (Box 17)
    - Libretti:pencil copy (Box 17)
    - Libretti: typed with revisions (Box 17)
    - Libretti: typed (Box 17)
    - Piano vocal score with some revisions (Box 17)
    - Orchestral score (bound in two volumes) (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - "Final Version" (with revisions) of piano vocal score (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Piano vocal score (transparencies) (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Piano vocal score with revisions and sketches (Box 18 (Oversize))
    - Program (world premier) (Box 19)
    - Set design (Box 19)
    - Chamber orchestra version (ink copy of orchestral score) (Box 19)
    - Sketches (Box 20)
    - Worksheets (4 books) (Box 20)
    - Proof of orchestral score-wrapped in two groups (Box 20)
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Pencil holograph (parts- strings, clarinet, and flute) (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Synopsis and program (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Spiral-bound piano vocal score (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Spiral-bound photocopy of piano vocal score (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Spiral-bound mimeograph of full score (Box 21 (Oversize))
    - Parts (ink) (Box 22)
  - Foundation of violin playing
    - Ink holograph (Box 23)
    - 3 sketchbooks (Box 23)
    - Forward and sketches (Box 23)
    - Transparencies (Box 23)
    - 2 bound copies (Box 23)
  - From the American folklore
    - Ink copy (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Pencil copy and program notes (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Worksheets (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Orchestral parts (2 groups) (Box 24 (Oversize))
    - Orchestral parts (3 bound volumes) (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Holiday mood (See also "Divertimento for orchestra, Movement 3")
    - Worksheets (Box 25)
    - Proofs (Box 25)
    - Cover (Box 25)
    - Transparencies (score and solo part) (Box 25)
    - Mimeograph (score and solo part) (Box 25)
    - Published copy (Box 25)
  - An invocation
    - Original pencil copy (Box 26)
    - Sketches (Box 26)
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 26)
    - Orchestra parts (2 envelopes) (Box 26)
    - Text (Box 26)
    - 2 mimeograph copies of the full score (Box 26)
  - Landscape and dance
    - Pencil copy (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (score)? (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Légende for violin and piano
    - 2 published copies (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Pencil holograph (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - 1st and 2nd proofs of solo parts (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Légende for elementary school band (In the style of a Russian folksong)
    - Photo-positives and ink holograph of piano part (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Pencil holograph (score) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Photo-positives (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Ink holograph (score and parts) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Clarinet part from Légende for elementary school band- not found (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - "Concertante"- not found (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Lethe
    - Holograph (pencil) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Sketches (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - New copy (ink) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Photo-positive (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Photocopy (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Melody with variations
    - Ink holograph (score) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Proofs (solo parts) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Proofs (solo clarinet and full score) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - 2nd proof, violin part (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 27 (Oversize))
    - Photo-positives (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - Morning music
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 31)
    - Ink holograph (parts) (Box 31)
    - Worksheets (Box 31)
    - Published copy (Box 31)
    - Programs (Box 31)
  - Music for violin alone
    - Bound mimeographed copy and transparencies (Box 32)
    - Sketches (pencil) (Box 32)
  - Nocturne for violin and piano
    - Proof (Box 32)
    - Ink holograph- not found here (Box 32)
    - Proof (score) (Box 32)
  - Octave study
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 32)
    - Orchestration (Box 32)
  - Passacaglia
    - Pencil holograph (Box 32)
  - Pastorale and dance
    - 1st proofs (2 clarinet and 2 violin parts) (Box 32)
    - Transparencies (score and parts) (Box 32)
    - 1st proof of full score- not found here (Box 32)
    - Sketches (Box 32)
    - Proofs (score and parts) (Box 32)
    - 2nd proof (score) (Box 32)
  - Poem for violin and string quartet
    - Manuscript and worksheets (Box 33)
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 33)
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 33)
    - Photo-positives (2 envelopes) (Box 33)
    - Photocopy (Box 33)
    - Ink holograph (2 groups) (Box 33)
  - Retirement concert
    - Program, 24 Apr 1966 (Box 33)
  - Quartets, strings, no. 1 (Other title: "Quatuor")
    - Mimeograph and pencil holograph (Box 33)
    - Photo-positive of copyist's manuscript (Box 33)
    - Ink holograph (Box 33)
  - Quartets, strings, no. 2
    - Score (mimeograph) (Box 57)
    - Parts (mimeographed original? and copyists) (Box 57)
    - Prints (Box 57)
    - Worksheets and sketches and pencil holograph (Box 57)
    - Programs (Box 57)
    - Bound published library copy (no. 2) (Box 57)
  - Quartets, strings, no. 3
    - Transparencies (parts) (Box 34)
    - Transparencies (score) (Box 34)
    - Corrections (Box 34)
  - Russian dance
    - Published copy (Box 34)
  - Serenade for saxophone, bassoon, and 'cello (Other title: "Music for saxophone, bassoon, and 'cello")
    - Mimeograph of ink holograph (bassoon and cello parts) (Box 34)
    - Pencil holograph (score) (Box 34)
  - Sinfonietta
    - Sketches- 26 pages and pencil holograph 3 booklets- 64 pages (Box 34)
  - Solitude (Other title: Poem nocturne "Solitide")
    - Individual orchestra parts- 2 envelopes (Box 35)
    - Original pencil holograph of the orchestra score- 43 pages (Box 35)
    - Orchestra score- 2 copies (Box 35)
  - Sonata for piano and violin (1928)
    - Ink holograph- solo violin part (Box 36)
    - Photocopy- solo violin part (Box 36)
    - Pencil holograph (1st and 3rd movements) (Box 36)
    - 3 scores- different versions (Box 36)
  - Sonata no. 2 for violin and piano
    - Ink holograph (score and solo part) (Box 37)
    - Sketches, working copy (Box 37)
    - Transparencies (Box 37)
    - Ink holograph (Box 37)
  - Sonata for violin and cello
    - Proof of full score (Box 38)
    - Proof of full score (green) (Box 38)
    - Transparencies (Box 38)
    - Worksheets and sketches (Box 38)
    - Special prints for violin part (Box 38)
    - 1st proof (Box 38)
    - Ink holograph (Box 38)
  - Sonatina for piano
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 39)
    - Published copy (Box 39)
    - Bound copy (Box 39)
    - Transparencies (Box 39)
    - Proofs (Box 39)
  - Sonatina for two pianos
    - Ink copy (Box 39)
    - One page from Sonatina for two pianos (Box 39)
  - Sonnet for organ
    - Pencil copy (Box 39)
    - Transparencies (Box 39)
    - Sketches and worksheets (26 pages) (Box 39)
    - Published copy (Box 39)
    - Ink copy (Box 39)
  - Symphonic movement for orchestra and violin obligato (Other title: "Mouvement symphonique")
    - Parts (Box 40 (Oversize))
    - Bound orchestral score (Box 40 (Oversize))
    - Pencil holographs- 2 envelopes (Box 40 (Oversize))
    - Published copy (Box 40 (Oversize))
    - Proofs (Box 40 (Oversize))
  - Symphonic rhapsody for the band (Other titles: "Rhapsody for symphonic band," "Symphonic rhapsody for the band" and "Rhapsody for band")
    - Manuscript (condensed score)- 23 pages, worksheets, holograph of the full score in pencil- 43 pages (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - Pencil holograph (score) (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - Ink copy (parts) (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - 2 bound copies of full score (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - Individual orchestra parts (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - Transparencies (Box 41 (Oversize))
  - Symphony in C
    - Piano score holograph (65 pages) (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - 1 unbound photocopy of piano score (Box 41 (Oversize))
    - 1 spiral-bound photocopy of piano score (Box 41 (Oversize))
  - Symphony in C
    - 1 unbound ink copy (Box 42 (Oversize))
    - 2 spiral-bound ink copies (Box 42 (Oversize))
    - Photo-positive (Box 43)
    - Parts (1 of 2) (Box 43)
    - Parts (2 of 2) (Box 44)
  - Trio for flute, 'cello, and harp
    - Sketches (Box 45)
    - Worksheets (Box 45)
    - Proofs of score and parts (Box 45)
    - Ink holograph (score)- 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Ink holographs (parts) (Box 45)
    - Photocopy (part) (Box 45)
    - Photocopy (score) (Box 45)
  - Trio for piano, violin and 'cello
    - Transparencies (full score and parts) (Box 45)
    - Sketches (Box 45)
    - Worksheets (for 1st, 2nd, and 3rd movements) 3 envelopes (Box 45)
    - Proofs of score and parts- not found here (Box 45)
    - Pencil holographs 92 p. full scores- not found here (Box 45)
  - Valley Forge
    - Transparencies of individual orchestra parts (Box 46)
    - Letter from congressman (Box 46)
    - Pencil holograph (Box 46)
    - Sketches and worksheets (Box 46)
    - Score (2 copies- one bound, one loose sheets) (Box 46)
  - Words of cheer to Zion
    - Condensed score and worksheets- 37 pages (Box 46)
    - Score for mixed chorus with piano accompaniment- not found (Box 46)
    - Text (Box 46)
    - Transparencies (Box 46)
  - You never know
    - Spiral-bound score (Box 46)
    - Holograph-loose leaf binder (Box 47)
    - Transparencies (Box 47)
    - Libretto, (2 envelopes) (Box 47)
    - Libretto (Box 48)
    - Libretto -transparencies (Box 48)
    - Auto-positives (Box 48)
    - Libretto-pencil holograph (Box 48)
    - Sketches (Box 48)
    - Piano reduction with vocal part (Box 49)
    - Orchestral score - transparencies (Box 49)
    - Published copy of the piano reduction (Box 49)
    - Work copy (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Sketches and sketchbooks, (3 envelopes) (Box 28)
    - Newspaper clipping (Box 28)
    - Bound sketchbook (Box 28)
    - Worksheets, (1 envelope) (Box 28)
    - 1 loose leaf book (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous photo-positives (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous sketches, (2 envelopes) (Box 29)
    - 4 sketchbooks (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous transparencies (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous pages 19 and 20 (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous worksheets (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous scores (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous scores - envelope titled "Sonata for violin and 'cello" but score for violin and piano (Box 30)
- SERIES II. Recordings
  - Chausson, Ernest — Concerto for violin and piano. I, II, III Movements, Boris Koutzen, (violinist), John Crouch (pianist), Vassar College, Skinner Hall, 1956 Feb 2; (reel-to-reel, 2 copies) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-1))
  - Debussy, Claude — Danse sacrée et [danse] profane, circa 1950s; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-5))
  - Fauré, Gabriel— Sonata for violin and piano. (John Crouch and Boris Koutzen), undated; (reel-to-reel, 2 copies) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-6))
  - Haydn, Joseph — 4th movement / Sibelius, Vassar College Orchestra, 1959 May 6; (LP, 33 1/3 rpm) (Box 51 (K#51LP-2))
  - Koutzen, Boris — 1st string quartet in Bb major — NBC String Quartet, 1942 Nov 8; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-24))
  - Koutzen, Boris — 2nd string quartet — NBC Broadcast, Primrose String Quartet, 1941 Mar 30; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-25))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 1) — I. "String Quartet No. 3 (1944)" performed by the Hudson Valley String Quartet and II. "Sonnet for Organ (1946)" performed by Kathleen Funk Pearson, 1966 Apr 24 (Box 52.a (K#52RR-12))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 2) — III. "Trio for Flute, Cello and Harp (1933)" performed by Paul Boyer, Sterling Hunkins, and Susan Jolles and IV. "Poem for Violin Solo and String Quartet (1963)" performed by Nadia Koutzen and the Hudson Valley String Quartet, 1966 Apr 24; (reel-to-reel, original) (Box 52.b (K#52RR-28))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 2) — III. "Trio for Flute, Cello and Harp (1933)" performed by Paul Boyer, Sterling Hunkins, and Susan Jolles and IV. "Poem for Violin Solo and String Quartet (1963)" performed by Nadia Koutzen and the Hudson Valley String Quartet, 1966 Apr 24; (CD copy) (Box 52.b (K#52CD-1))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 2) — III. "Trio for Flute, Cello and Harp (1933)" performed by Paul Boyer, Sterling Hunkins, and Susan Jolles and IV. "Poem for Violin Solo and String Quartet (1963)" performed by Nadia Koutzen and the Hudson Valley String Quartet, 1966 Apr 24; (reel-to-reel, copy) (Box 52.b (K#52RR-29))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 2) — III. "Trio for Flute, Cello and Harp (1933)" performed by Paul Boyer, Sterling Hunkins, and Susan Jolles and IV. "Poem for Violin Solo and String Quartet (1963)" performed by Nadia Koutzen and the Hudson Valley String Quartet, 1966 Apr 24; (CD copy) (Box 52.b (K#52CD-2))
  - Koutzen, Boris — A concert of compositions by Boris Koutzen (Part 3) — V. "Dreamland - for voice and piano (1964)" performed by Albert and Huguette van Ackere and VI. "Sonatina for Two Pianos (1944)" performed by Gwendolyn Hamilton and Earl Groves, 1966 Apr 24 (Box 52.a (K#52RR-13))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Concerto for five solo instruments and string orchestra, Vassar College Orchestra, 1961 May 7; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-11))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Dreamland and Sonatina for Two Pianos (original), [1966?]; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-4))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Elegiac Rhapsody, Vassar College Orchestra, 1963 May 1; (reel-to-reel, 2 copies) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-8))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Fanfare, prayer and march, Vassar College Orchestra, Koutzen conducting, 1965 May 5; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.b (K#52RR-27))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Fanfare, prayer and march, Vassar College Orchestra, Koutzen conducting, undated; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-14))
  - Koutzen, Boris — An invocation (rehearsal), Vassar College Glee Club and Orchestra, 1959 May 5; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-16))
  - Koutzen, Boris — An invocation (performance), Vassar, 1959 May 6; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-17))
  - Koutzen, Boris — An Invocation, Vassar College Glee Club and Chappaqua Chamber Orchestra, Koutzen conducting, 1959 May 16; (LP, 33 1/3 rpm) (Box 51 (K#51LP-3))
  - Koutzen, Boris — An invocation for women's' voices and orchestra, Vassar Glee Club and the Chappaqua Chamber Orchestra, Koutzen conducting, 1959 May 16; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-18))
  - Koutzen, Boris — An invocation, "Vassar and [Philadelphia] Orchestra,", [1959?]; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-19))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Morning music for flute and string orchestra, Philadelphia Conservatory Orchestra, Koutzen conducting, circa 1950s; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-20))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Sonata for violin and cello, Koutzen and Shapiro, 1958 Nov 13; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-21))
  - Koutzen, Boris — "Sinfonietta" and "Concerto for viola and orchestra," The Knickerbocker Chamber Players, circa 1950s; (LP, 33 1/3 rpm) (Box 51 (K#51LP-1))
  - Koutzen, Boris — String quartet no. 3 (1944) — Hudson Valley String Quartet / Sonnet for Organ (1946) — Kathleen Funk Pearson, organ, [1966?]; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.b (K#52RR-26))
  - Koutzen, Boris — Valley Forge Symphonic Poem — I. Broadcast, NBC Symphony (Sep 8, 1940) — II. Broadcast, The Cleveland Orchestra (Feb 21, 1942), 1940, 1942; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-23))
  - [Simons, Netty] — Sonata for 2 violins, [circa 1950-1970?]; (reel-to-reel) (Box 52.a (K#52RR-22))
  - Excerpts from an unknown radio broadcast, circa 1930-1945; (LP, 33 1/3 rpm) (Box 51 (K#51LP-13))